Finding Aid for Executive Vice-President and Chief Financial Officer (University of Michigan) publications.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Executive Vice-President and Chief Financial Officer (University of Michigan) publications 1917-2014, 1952-2013
University of Michigan. Executive Vice-President and Chief Financial Officer.
26 linear feet
9747 Bimu B6 2
Executive Vice-President and Chief Financial Officer publications includes the general university budgets in addition to budgets for the University Hospital and the residence halls. Also contains appropriation requests, audit reports, capital outlay reports, and department payrolls and accounts. Also includes financial reports and reports of investments.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Publications are received periodically from the unit.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The record group is open to research.
Please consult the history found in the finding aid for Executive Vice-President and Chief Financial Officer (University of Michigan) Records.
The Publications series of the Vice President and Chief Financial Officer is divided into two subseries: Unit Publications and Sub-Unit Publications. The Unit Publications subseries is divided into Budgets and Reports. The publications includes the general university budgets in addition to budgets for the University Hospital and the residence halls as well as appropriation requests, audit reports, capital outlay reports, and department payrolls and accounts. Also included are financial reports and reports of investments.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Vice-President and Chief Financial Officer.; University of Michigan. Office of Financial Analysis and Cost Reimbursement.; University of Michigan. Executive Vice-President and Chief Financial Officer.; University of Michigan. Investment Office.; University of Michigan--Finance.; University of Michigan--Planning.; University of Michigan--Employees--Salaries, etc.; University of Michigan--Faculty--Salaries, etc.
Contributors:
University of Michigan. Vice-President and Chief Financial Officer.; University of Michigan. Office of Financial Analysis and Cost Reimbursement.; University of Michigan. Investment Office.
Genre Terms:
Budgets.; Reports.
- Unit Publications
  - Budgets
    The need for multiple copies led university officials in 1919/20 to print copies of most of the budget. Between 1919/20 and 1947/48 this bound record was divided into two parts. Part I Summary of the Budget, gave a quick overview of university general fund spending. Part II, Salary Budget, detailed the largest item in the general fund budget. The Salary Budget omitted, however, all non-salary expenses and the optional explanation of changes.
    In 1948/49 the printed budget was modified. The Salary Budget was retitled Detailed Budget and its scope was broadened. Non-salary items previously excluded, such as "Current Expense and Equipment" and "Travel" were reported, as well as a few general fund accounts which earlier had not been detailed. A growing concern over the privacy of individual salary figures, led to a major revision in the budget's format in 1956/57. The Summary Budget, for convenience long published as a separate document, became the only published document.
    In place of the Detailed Budget a new publication, called Department Payroll and Accounts, appeared. This document, which had only a limited distribution, included the salary information formerly printed in section II. This salary information also appears in the pages of the Michigan Daily which, based upon legislation enacted in October 1979 defined state employees' salaries as public records, has annually published the salaries of faculty and professional and administrative employees of the university. In university records salary information, dating from 1956 through 1971, will be found under the heading "Reports" under the title Departmental Payroll and Accounts. They include a list of all employees arranged by department and their salaries. These reports also note faculty sabbaticals and leaves. For later salary lists the researcher should consult the finding aid for: University of Michigan. Office of Human Resources and Affirmative Action. Publications.
    In 1957/58, although the Summary Budget continued to be published, a more complete publication Proposed Budget and Supplementary Schedules was begun. It included the information found in the general fund budget, as well as information about project budgets. This new publication, referred to informally as "the grey book" because of its cover, became the basic budgetary reference tool. In 1965/66 the volume's title was changed to Budget and Supplementary Schedules. In 1967/68 it became known by the simple title, Budgets. In 1973/74 the grey book was divided into four volumes, one subtitled "All Campus," the other three giving the budget for each of the university's three major centers, Ann Arbor, Dearborn, and Flint. The general university budgets are arranged chronologically beginning in 1920 through the present.
    Compared with the complexity of the publications reflecting the university's annual general fund budget, the Trust Fund Budget is simple. There are several volumes for the period from 1948/49 through 1967/68 in the PUBLICATIONS series. This, however, is not a complete run. The manuscript Trust Fund Budgets are found in boxes 34-50 of the manuscript records of the University of Michigan Vice President and Chief Financial Officer and should be consulted for more complete information.
    The budgets of the residence halls and University Hospital have been retained because they are the university's largest auxiliary activities. The hospital, for example, usually accounts for twenty to twenty-five percent of the university's total income and expenses. They are similar in form to the printed annual budget's Detailed Section. The hospital budget contains primarily salary information and also a few general financial tables. It seems to have been modeled on the older official copy of the university budget.
    - Budget for the Year Ending June 30,...
      - 1920-1933, 14 volumes (Box 1)
        (includes salaries)
      - 1934-1944, 11 volumes (Box 2)
      - 1945-1951, 7 volumes (Box 3)
      - 1952-1956, 5 volumes (Box 4)
    - Budget of the General Fund for the Year...
      - 1954/55-1957/58, 4 volumes (Box 5)
    - Proposed Budget and Supplementary Schedules for the Year...
      - 1957/58-1960/61, 4 volumes (Box 5)
    - Budget and Supplementary Schedules for the Year...
      - 1961/62-1966/67, 6 volumes (Box 5)
    - Budgets
      - 1967/68-1972/73, 6 volumes (Box 5)
    - Budgets (Box 6)
      - 1973/74-1982/83, 10 folders (Box 6)
        (includes 1 volume for each--All-Campuses, Ann Arbor, Dearborn, and Flint)
      - 1983/84-1985/86, 3 volumes (Box 6)
      - 1986/87-1994/95, 10 volumes (Box 7)
        (including 1989/90 Budget Presentation)
      - 1995/96-2002/2003, 7 volumes (Box 8)
        (continues in Box 24)
      - 2003/2004-2014/2015, 12 volumes (Box 24)
    - Budgets of University Hospital, Neuropsychiatric Institute, and Veterans Readjustment Center (Box 9)
      - 1952/53 (Box 9)
    - Residence Halls Budget 1940/41-1954/55, 16 volumes (Box 9)
    - Residence Halls Budget, 1955/56-1965/66, 11 volumes (Box 10)
    - Trust Funds
      - Budgets for Auxiliary Activities and Certain Trust Fund Accounts 1964-1967, 3 folders (Box 10)
      - Budgets for Certain Trust Units
        - 1955/56-1957/58, 3 volumes (Box 10)
      - Budgets for Certain Trust Units, 1960/61-1963/64, 4 volumes (Box 11)
      - Certain Budgets of Auxiliary Activities and Trust Fund Accounts, 1967/68 (Box 11)
      - Trust Fund Budgets, 1948/49-1951/52, 4 folders (Box 11)
  - Reports
    Reports include appropriation requests, audits, and capital outlay reports prepared by the vice president for transmission to the state government, primarily to the legislature. Other reports include: Commitments, Frequency Distribution of Commitments, and Flexible Funds Balance Estimate; Departmental Payrolls and Accounts (General Fund and Auxiliary activities); Financial Information Detail by Account; and most important, the annual financial report.
    The Appropriation Requests date from 1948 to 1973. They are arranged chronologically under a variety of titles. These reports were sent to the state legislature requesting funds for the operation of the university and are filled with information regarding the financial needs of the university and the plans of the administration to fulfill the goals of the university. Appropriations Requests, 1967-1973 contain requests for state appropriations, as approved by the Regents for 1967, 1968 and 1969 as well as requests for special appropriations for the Medical School and the Institute for Gerontology.
    There are only scattered audit reports for the university as a whole. They are arranged alphabetically by title. However, there are several financial statements and audit reports for specific units. These reports are arranged alphabetically under the unit.
    The capital outlay reports are arranged chronologically under various titles. Mandated by Public Act no. 116 of 1953, they include not only the annual capital outlay report, but also long-range planning for the upcoming five-year period. These reports begin in 1953 and continue through 1974-1975. Beginning in 1970-1971 there are separate volumes for the Ann Arbor, Dearborn, and Flint campuses.
    Originally prepared for the regents' scrutiny, today the annual financial reports are the basic documents through which the university makes itself accountable for the receipt and expenditure of funds. Two types are generated: Financial (originally Treasurer's) and Investment. The Financial Report, and its predecessor Treasurer's Report, has been issued annually since 1883. For earlier Treasurer's Report the researcher should consult the finding aid for: University of Michigan. Treasurer. Publications.
    The annual financial reports are arranged chronologically dating from 1917 through the present. Their titles vary. The later financial reports include a Report of Independent Auditors. Originally, the financial report was one volume. In 1975 the Financial Report was published in two parts. The first offers a cursory overview of all university income and expenses regardless of the source. The second presents tables detailing income and expenses at the unit level. Because the Financial Report includes both general fund and project income and details both summary salary and non-salary expenses, it is the single most comprehensive document available regarding university finances.
    - Appropriation Requests
      - Request for State Appropriations for Operations for 1949-1950 and 1950-1951, 1948 (Box 11)
      - Appropriation Request for 1953-1954 Building Construction and Building Rehabilitation at the University of Michigan, October 1952 (Box 11)
      - Appropriation Requests of the University of Michigan for the Fiscal Year 1954-1955, September 1953 (Box 11)
      - University of Michigan Appropriation Request for 1954-1955 for Building Construction, Remodeling and Additions, and Special Maintenance, September 1953 (Box 11)
      - Appropriation Request for 1955-1956 for Building Construction, Remodeling and Additions, and Special Maintenance, September 1954 (Box 11)
      - The University of Michigan Requests a Separate Appropriation of $1,005,000 for Research and Service in the Utilization of Human Resources for the Year 1956-1957, October 1955 (Box 11)
      - Summary of 1957-1958 Appropriations Requests for Operations, October 1956 (Box 11)
      - The University of Michigan Needs an Increase in Legislative Appropriations for Operations of $6,621,458 for 1957-1958, November 1956 (Box 11)
      - The University of Michigan Needs an Increase in Legislative Appropriations for Operations of $6,788,270 for 1959-1960, October 1958 (Box 11)
      - The University of Michigan Needs an Increase in Legislative Appropriations for Operations, of $5,827,718 for 1960-1961 October 1959 (Box 11)
      - The University of Michigan Requests a Legislative Appropriation of $43,620,652 for Operations during Year 1962-1963 October 1961 (Box 11)
      - Appropriation Request for 1965-1966, 1965 [Draft] (Box 11)
      - Request for General Fund Appropriations for Operations 1967-1968, September 1966 (Box 11)
      - Request for General Fund Appropriations for Operations 1970-1971, October 1969 (Box 11)
      - Summary of the Request for General Fund Appropriations for Operations 1970-1971, November 1969 (Box 11)
      - Request for General Fund Appropriations for Operations 1971-1972 (Ann Arbor, Dearborn, and Flint), October 1970, 3 folders (Box 12)
    - Appropriation Requests 1967-1973
      - Request for General Fund Appropriations for Operations 1968-1969, October 1967 (Box 25)
      - The University of Michigan 1969-1970 Appropriations Request for Operations October 1968 (Box 25)
      - The University of Michigan Supplemental Information to Request for Appropriations 1969-1970, February 1969 (Box 25)
      - Request for General Fund Appropriations for Operations 1970-1971 [Dearborn Campus], October 1969 (Box 25)
      - Special Request for the Medical School, 1969-1970 1969 (Box 25)
      - The Institute of Gerontology 1970-1971 Appropriations Request for Operations 1969 (Box 25)
      - The Institute of Gerontology 1971-1972 Appropriations Request for Operations 1970 (Box 25)
    - Audits
      - University of Michigan, Ann Arbor
        - Audit Report: University of Michigan, July 1, 1965-June 30, 1966, 1968 (Box 12)
        - Audited Financial Statements
          - June 30, 1965 (Box 12)
        - Financial Statements and Report
          - June 30, 1958 (Box 12)
        - Management Letter [from Auditors]
          - June 30, 1987 (Box 12)
        - Report of Examination With Supplementary Data
          - 1947-1948, 2 volumes (Box 12)
      - Financial Statements and Audit Reports
        - General including Combined, Athletics, Hospitals and Medical Service Plans 1986-1989, 3 folders (Box 12)
        - Specific Units
          - Alumni Association
            - June 30, 1965 (Box 12)
            - 1967 (Box 12)
            - 1986-1989, 3 folders (Box 12)
          - Board for Student Publications 1987-1988 (Box 12)
          - M-Care 1986-1988, 2 volumes (Box 12)
          - Student Financial Assistance Programs 1987-1988 (Box 12)
          - University of Michigan Hospitals 1987-1988 (Box 12)
          - Veritas Insurance Corporation 1986-1988, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Capital Outlay Reports
      - University of Michigan Five-Year Capital Outlay Program, 1954-1955 to 1958-1959, 1953 (Box 12)
      - University of Michigan Five-Year Capital Outlay Program and 1956-1957 Appropriation Request for New Building Construction, Remodeling and Additions, and Special Maintenance, 1955 (Box 12)
      - University Hospital Five-Year Capital Outlay Program and 1956-1957 Appropriation Request for New Building Construction and Remodeling and Additions, September 1955 (Box 12)
      - University of Michigan Five-Year Capital Outlay Program and 1957-1958 Appropriation Request for New Building Construction, Remodeling and Additions, and Special Maintenance, 1956 (Box 12)
      - University Hospital Five-Year Capital Outlay Program and 1957-1958 Appropriation Request for New Building Construction and Remodeling and Additions, 1956 (Box 12)
      - Capital Outlay Budget Agency Requests and Needs for the Five-Year Period Fiscal Year 1958-1959 Through 1962-1963 1957 (Box 12)
      - Capital Outlay Budget Agency Requests and Needs for the Five-Year Period Fiscal Year 1959-1960 Through 1963-1964 1958 (Box 12)
      - Capital Outlay Budget Agency Requests and Needs for the Five-Year Period Fiscal Year 1960-1961 Through 1964-1965 1959 (Box 13)
      - Capital Outlay Budget Agency Requests and Needs for the Five-Year Period Fiscal Year 1961-1962 Through 1965-1966 1960 (Box 13)
      - Capital Outlay Budget Agency Requests and Needs for the Five-Year Period Fiscal Year 1962-1963 Through 1966-1967 1961 (Box 13)
      - Capital Outlay Budget Agency Requests and Needs for the Five-Year Period Fiscal Year 1963-1964 Through 1967-1968 1962 (Box 13)
      - Capital Outlay Budget Agency Requests and Needs for the Five-Year Period Fiscal Year 1964-1965 Through 1968-1969, 1963 (Box 13)
      - Capital Outlay Request 1965-66 Five-Year Program 1965-1970 1964 (Box 13)
      - Capital Outlay Budget Request including The Long-Range Needs for the Five-Year Period 1966-1967 Through 1970-1971 1965 (Box 13)
      - 1967-1968 Capital Outlay Budget Request including The Long-Range Needs for the Five-Year Period 1967-1968 Through 1971-1972, 1966 (Box 13)
      - 1968-1969 Capital Outlay Budget Request including The Long-Range Needs for the Five-Year Period 1968-1969 Through 1972-1973, 1967 (Box 13)
      - 1969-1970 Capital Outlay Budget Request including The Long-Range Needs for Five-Year Period 1969-1970 Through 1973-1974, 1968 (Box 13)
      - 1970-1971 Capital Outlay Budget Request including The Long-Range Needs for Five-Year Period 1970-1971 Through 1974-1975, 1969, 2 volumes covering Ann Arbor, Flint and Dearborn (Box 13)
      - 1971-1972 Capital Outlay Budget Request...including The Long-Range Needs for Five-Year Period 1971-1972 Through 1975-1976, 1970, 3 volumes covering Ann Arbor, Dearborn and Flint (Box 13)
      - 1972-1973 Capital Outlay Budget Request...including The Long-Range Needs for Five-Year Period 1972-1973 Through 1976-1977, 1971, 4 volumes covering Ann Arbor, Dearborn and Flint,;the Medical Center (Box 13)
      - 1973-1974 Capital Outlay Budget Request...including The Long-Range Needs for Five-Year Period 1973-1974 Through 1977-1978, 1972, 4 volumes (Box 13)
        (covering Ann Arbor, Dearborn, Flint, and the Medical Center)
      - 1974-1975 Capital Outlay Budget Request...including The Long-Range Needs for Five-Year Period 1974-1975 Through 1978-1979 1973, 4 volumes (Box 13)
    - Commitments, Frequency Distribution of Commitments, and Flexible Funds Balance Estimate, 1987-1988, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Departmental Payrolls and Accounts
      - 1956-1959, 3 folders (Box 13)
    - Departmental Payrolls and Accounts General Fund, 1959-1962, 3 folders (Box 14)
    - Departmental Payrolls and Accounts General Fund and Auxiliary Activities, 1962-1965 no Auxiliary Activities for 1964-1965, 5 folders (Box 14)
    - Departmental Payrolls and Accounts General Fund, 1965-1968, 3 volumes (Box 15)
    - Departmental Payrolls and Accounts, 1968-1970, 2 volumes (Box 15)
    - Departmental Payrolls and Accounts, 1970-1971, 1 volumes (Box 16)
    - Endowment and Student Loan Funds of the University of Michigan, 1962 (Box 16)
    - Financial Information Detail by Account, 1985-1987, 2 volumes (Box 16)
    - Financial Reports, Annual
      - Financial Report of the University of Michigan For the Year Ended June 30,...
        - 1917-1945, 5 volumes (Box 16)
      - Financial Report of the University of Michigan For the Year Ended June 30,... (Box 17)
        - 1946-1960, 3 volumes (Box 17)
      - University of Michigan Financial Report...Year Ended June 30th
        - 1961-1962, 2 volumes (Box 17)
      - University of Michigan Financial Report...Year Ended June 30th
        - 1963-1979, 24 volumes (Box 17)
      - University of Michigan Financial Report...Year Ended June 30th (Box 18)
        - 1980-2000, 44 volumes (Box 18)
        - 2000-ongoing (Box 25)
    - Financial Reports, Final, 1987 (Box 19)
    - Program Budget Evaluation System
      - Base Program Request, October 1972 (Box 19)
      - Institution Program Plan, May 1972 (Box 19)
      - Program Revision Requests for the Ann Arbor Campus, 1972 (Box 19)
      - 1974-1975 Budget Request Ann Arbor Campus, October 1973 (Box 19)
    - Year-End Financial Information
      - 1983-1984 (Box 19)
      - 1986-1987 (Box 19)
      - 1988-1989 (Box 19)
    - Response to State Budget Office Guidelines 1969-1970 [Working Draft], September 1968 (Box 25)
    - State Appropriations for Buildings 1973 (Box 25)
    - The University of Michigan Student Residences with Income Pledged, Financial Statements and Supplementary Information, with Report of Certified Public Accountants, (Arthur Young & Co) June 30, 1977 (Box 26)
    - The University of Michigan Student Residences with Income Pledged, Financial Statements and Supplementary Information, with Report of Independent Accountants, (Price Waterhouse & Co.) June 30, 1979 (Box 26)
    - The University of Michigan Student Residences with Income Pledged, Financial Statements and Supplementary Information, with Report of Independent Accountants, (Price Waterhouse & Co.) June 30, 1980 (Box 26)
    - Editors of Michigan Endorse University's Budget Request 1949 (Large poster with articles about the University's Budget from many different local newspapers around the state) (Box 26)
    - The University of Michigan: Its Programs and Needs, 1966-67 (Box 26)
- Sub-Unit Publications
  Sub-Unit Publications include reports from the Investment Office and budget analyses from the Office of Financial Analysis and Cost Reimbursement.
  The Investment Report is a highly specialized document which annually details where the university has placed the funds available to it. Begun in 1928 the Investment Report provides a detailed list of all investments the University of Michigan made and the value of those investments. In the mid-1960s the basic structure of the document was changed. Individual accounts were no longer listed. Instead, the university's investment portfolio was reported on as a whole, although the practice of citing each investment instrument by name was retained. The new format made it clear how university funds as a whole were invested, but made it impossible to determine where the funds of a particular account were placed. The Schedule of Investments covers the period from 1968 through 1989. It provides a detailed list of the University of Michigan's investments including the names of companies and the book and market values of the university's various investments.
  - Investment Office
    - Reports
      - Investment Objectives and Procedures for Endowment Funds, 1952 (Box 19)
      - Investment Reviews
        - Review of Investment Programs, 1974-1975, 2 folders (Box 19)
        - Investment Review, 1975-1978, 5 folders (Box 19)
      - Report of Investments, June 30,... (Box 20)
        - 1928-1931 Investments of All Deposit Accounts and Trust Funds, 1 volumes (Box 20)
        - 1932-1934 Investment of All Trust Fund and Deposit Accounts, 1 volumes (Box 20)
        - 1935-1938 Report of Investments of Trust Funds and Deposit Accounts, 1 volumes (Box 20)
        - 1939-1944, Report of Investments of Trust Funds and Deposit Accounts, 1 volumes (Box 20)
        - 1945-1950, Report of Investments of Trust Funds and Deposit Accounts, 1 volumes (Box 20)
        - 1951-1955 Report of Investments, 1 volumes (Box 21)
        - 1956-1982 Report of Investments, 25 volumes (Box 21)
        - 1983-1991 Report of Investments, 15 volumes (Box 22)
        - 1994 (Box 26)
        - 1996 (Box 26)
        - 1999 (Box 26)
        - 2003 (Box 26)
      - Report of Investments, December 31,...
        - 1930-1933 Trust Fund Investments, 4 volumes (Box 22)
        - 1934-1935 Report of Investments of Trust Funds and Deposit Accounts, 2 volumes (Box 22)
        - 1943-1944 Report of Investments of Trust Funds and Deposit Accounts, 2 volumes (Box 22)
      - Report on University's Investment Program and Policies, 1952 (Box 22)
      - Review of Investments
        - 1952-1955 Review of Investment Program for the Major Endowment Funds, 6 volumes (Box 22)